Finding Aid for the J. Paul Getty Family Collected Papers, circa 1880s-1989, undated IA20009
Institutional Records and Archives
- George F. Getty I and Sarah C. Getty papers, 1890; 1904-1921,; 1928,; 1931-1934,; 1939,; undated; (bulk 1911-1912); Series II.; 1 Linear Feet (6 boxes)
  In 1903 George traveled from Minneapolis on legal business to Bartlesville in the Indian Territory (a region annexed in 1907 by the United State government to create the state of Oklahoma). There he began his career in the petroleum industry by leasing "Lot 50" in the Osage Nation and incorporating the Minnehoma Oil Company. In 1905 the Getty family moved to Los Angeles, in the hope that the warm, dry climate of California would improve Sarah's health. George and Sarah soon built a Tudor-style home at the corner of Wilshire Boulevard and South Kingsley Drive in Los Angeles, which was maintained as a primary residence until Sarah's death in 1941.
  George tended his growing oil business in Oklahoma and elsewhere, traveling periodically from the family home in Los Angeles to the oil fields, sometimes accompanied by Paul and Sarah. By 1907 George had ceased to practice law and was focused on his oil business. He established an office at the Union Oil Building (at 7th and Spring streets) in Los Angeles in 1913. George employed family members in his oil business, including his brother, "D. L." Getty; his sister Belle's husband, J. Carl Smith; and his sister Laura's husband, H. L. Allen.
  George died in 1930, leaving controlling interest of the family oil business to Sarah.
  Material comprises personal and professional papers of George Franklin Getty I and Sarah C. Getty, parents of Jean Paul Getty ("Paul"). Material dates from 1890 to 1939 and includes letters, telegrams, hand-drawn maps, cancelled stock certificates, contracts, promissory notes, travel documents, receipts, and various forms of ephemera. The family correspondence includes letters written by J. Paul Getty to his parents that provide insight into the personal and early business relationships between George, Paul, and Sarah. While the family correspondence hints at the atmosphere of the Getty household, George's papers shed light on his early oil operations, including scouting potential drilling sites, day-to-day management of drilling activities, and his political efforts to protect his interests/land in the Osage Nation (part of the territory that the United States government annexed in 1907 to form the state of Oklahoma). Sarah's mostly peripheral involvement in the family business is evinced by her correspondence with George and several notarized documents. Please note that although Sarah signed personal correspondence "Sara," most of the notarized documents and J. Paul Getty's autobiography spell her first name "Sarah," by which she is more commonly known.
  - George F. Getty I papers, 1890; 1904-1921,; 1928,; undated; (bulk 1911-1912); Series II.A.; 0.8 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
    Material is arranged by subject, beginning with family history and correspondence; followed by business and personal papers; concluding with ephemera and publications.
    Material comprises some personal and professional papers of George Franklin Getty I, father of Jean Paul Getty ("Paul"), dating 1890-1928 and undated. The family correspondence comprises letters received by George F. Getty I from various family members. The letters from his son, J. Paul Getty ("Paul"), primarily concern Paul's residence and travel abroad and usually include Paul's requests for funds. Letters from his wife, Sarah, address a blend of parenting, domestic, and business concerns. Because George employed his family in his business, letters from his siblings and other relatives contain news regarding family, real estate transactions, property management, and oil operations. The family history is an account of George Getty's ancestry as told by George's uncle, Joseph Getty.
    The business and personal papers provide a glimpse of George's early oil operations, including scouting potential drilling sites, day-to-day management of drilling activities, and political efforts to protect his interests/land in the Osage Nation, part of Indian Territory that the United States government annexed that later became the state of Oklahoma in 1907. Material includes letters, telegrams, hand-drawn maps, cancelled stock certificates, contracts, promissory notes, and other documents. Most of the letters are outgoing correspondence written by George F. Getty I. As was customary at the time, a reply to a letter is sometimes written directly on top of the original letter, thus a single sheet may contain an outgoing letter and its incoming response. The general incoming and outgoing correspondence are primarily related to property management, banking, and general business activities. Material also includes some papers that belonged to George's secretary, Mable McCreery.
    Material also includes dissociated ephemera collected by or related to George F. Getty I, including a paper-cut portrait of Mr. Getty and one loose-leaf, handmade scrapbook containing pressed fauna and flora, accompanied by short hand-written descriptions, which was likely sent to him by one of his relatives in Washington state.
    - Family history and correspondence, 1890; 1910-1915,; 1920,; undated; (bulk 1911-1912)
      Letters are arranged by correspondent in order of importance, beginning with George's son, J. Paul Getty. Each correspondent's letters are arranged chronologically. The letters are followed by a family history written by George's uncle, Joseph.
      - Letters from son, Paul, 1910-1915; 1920 (Box 2010.IA.17-02)
      - Letters from Paul, 1912-1913; 1920 (Box 2019.IA.56-01)
      - Letters from wife, Sarah, 1911-1912; undated (Box 2010.IA.17-02)
      - Letters from sister, Belle, 1911-1913; undated (Box 2010.IA.17-02)
      - Letters from brother, D. L. Getty, 1911-1912; undated (Box 2010.IA.17-02)
      - Letters from sister, Jennie V. Getty, 1913 (Box 2010.IA.17-02)
      - Letters from sister, Laura and her husband, H. L. Allen, 1911; 1912,; undated (Box 2010.IA.17-02)
        Includes one carbon copy of a letter written by George F. Getty to Laura.
      - Letters from other relatives, including correspondence written between relatives that is not addressed to George F. Getty, 1911; undated (Box 2010.IA.17-02)
      - Getty family history by Joseph Getty, handwritten original and transcription, April 16, 1890 (Box 2010.IA.17-02)
    - Business and personal papers, 1904-1921; 1928,; undated; (bulk 1911-1916)
      Material is arranged by subject, beginning with correspondence, followed by oil business papers and other personal papers.
      - Correspondence:
        - General incoming, 1909; 1911,; 1912,; 1914-1916,; 1920,; undated (Box 2010.IA.17-03)
        - General outgoing, 1911; 1914,; undated (Box 2010.IA.17-03)
        - With H. S. Lehr of Ohio State University regarding donations, 1911; 1912,; 1914 (Box 2010.IA.17-03)
      - Oil business papers:
        - Correspondence with scout, Ola J. Rogers, regarding oil field development, 1913-1914 (Box 2010.IA.17-03)
          Comprises letters, telegrams, and hand-drawn maps.
        - Correspondence regarding operations, 1911; 1912,; 1914,; 1919,; undated (Box 2010.IA.17-03)
          Material contains incoming letters and carbon copies of outgoing letters, including correspondence addressed to the United States government regarding George's holdings in Oklahoma and the fairness of certain taxes paid by oil producers.
        - Letters from U.S. Interior Secretary Lane regarding Osage oil and gas, 1915 (Box 2019.IA.56-01)
        - Stock certificate, contract, promissory note, and other notes, 1906; 1921,; 1928,; undated (Box 2010.IA.17-03)
        - Telegram/telegraph messages, primarily regarding oil business, 1911-1914; undated (Box 2010.IA.17-03)
      - Other personal papers:
        - Automobile purchases, maintenance, and related documents, 1911; 1912,; 1920,; undated (Box 2010.IA.17-03)
        - Document appointing George F. Getty District Deputy Grand Master for the Masonic Grand Lodge of St. Paul, Minnesota, February 5, 1904 (Box 2010.IA.17-04)
        - Real estate transactions, 1911; 1912,; undated (Box 2010.IA.17-03)
        - Travel document for George F. Getty, accompanied by his wife and minor son, issued by the United States of America Department of State, May 25, 1909 (Box 2010.IA.17-04)
        - Secretary Mabel McCreery Notary Public certificate and other McCreery documents, 1915-1917 (Box 2010.IA.17-02)
    - Ephemera and publications, 1911-1912; undated
      Material is arranged alphabetically by subject.
      - Business card, calling cards, and other identification cards, undated (Box 2010.IA.17-03)
      - Paper-cut silhouette (profile portrait) of George F. Getty, undated (Box 2010.IA.17-03)
      - Receipts (various), primarily from Brentwood Country Club, 1911-1912 (Box 2010.IA.17-03)
      - "Wildflowers of Washington" scrapbook, undated (Box 2010.IA.17-03)
      - Northern. Yearbook of Ohio Northern University, 1914 (Box 2012.IA.037-01)
      - Northern. Yearbook of Ohio Northern University, volume dedicated to George F. Getty., 1917 (Box 2012.IA.037-01)
  - Sarah C. Getty papers, 1908; 1909,; 1919,; 1921,; 1931-1934,; 1939,; undated; Series II.B.; 0.1 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
    Material comprises papers, with dates scattered between 1908 and 1939, once belonging to Sarah Catherine McPherson Risher Getty (1852-1941), including four letters, one postcard, and a souvenir booklet from her son, J. Paul Getty. Also included are two postcards from other relatives, a promissory note, and a few documents related to real estate development and water association stocks. Some documents are signed by both Sarah and her husband, George. Please note that although Sarah signed personal correspondence "Sara," most of the notarized documents and J. Paul Getty's autobiography spell her first name "Sarah," by which she is more commonly known.
    - Promissory note and other signed documents related to real estate development and water association stock, 1908; 1909,; 1919,; 1921 (Box 2010.IA.17-03)
    - Souvenir booklet "Views of Athens," signed "To Mother from Paul,", Christmas 1913; (17 colored prints of landmarks in and around Athens, Greece, mounted on green pages, and bound with a ribbon.) (Box 2010.IA.17-03)
    - Correspondence from son, Paul, 1931; 1934 (Box 2010.IA.17-03)
    - Letter from son Paul, 1933 (Box 2019.IA.56-01)
    - Postcard to Mrs. George F. Getty from her grandson, George F. Getty II and his mother, Jeannette, 1932 (Box 1986.IA.22-01, Folder 25)
    - Postcard of the Panama Canal from her grandson, George F. Getty II, 1939 (Box 2010.IA.17-03)
- Photographs, circa 1880s-1970s; Series III.; 2.4 Linear Feet (7 boxes containing over 100 unique images)
  The provenance of the photographs has been obscured by time. In an effort to improve access, the photographic prints and negatives in each accession are arranged in binders and roughly grouped by subject.
  Sets of photographic negatives, when present, have been placed at the back of the last binder of each accession. Sets have been assigned alphabetical identities by the Archives to facilitate retrieval. Rather than attempting to match the negatives with corresponding prints, these sets of negatives have been left in the order in which they were received.
  Individual negatives created by the Archives have been housed with their associated prints when possible.
  Materials consist primarily of black-and-white photographs and negatives, dating from approximately the 1880s to the 1970s, of J. Paul Getty, family, friends, properties, and city and landscape views. The materials also include several images of the J. Paul Getty Museum and galleries during its early years. The images are black-and-white unless otherwise specified.
  The images are of various sizes, and are largely undated and unidentified. The majority of these photographs once belonged to J. Paul Getty, while a smaller number of them seem to have belonged to his father, George F. Getty I. The photographs come from several different sources, including Ralph Hewins, Getty's biographer.
  When negatives were found together in an envelope they have been kept together in a set. The photographic prints, having arrived in the archives in a state of complete disarray, have been roughly organized by subject. Negatives can be found for some of the prints in this group of photographs and vice versa, but such relationships are uncommon.
  Please note that image counts are approximate and represent the number of unique images (not counting duplicates).
  - J. Paul Getty:
    - Portrait of J. Paul Getty as child, undated; (1 photographic negative) (Box 2010.IA.17-06, Section Set A)
    - J. Paul Getty in 8th grade class portrait, Emerson School, May 23, 1906; (1 photographic print) (Box Shared 1986.IA.22-02; 1987.IA.11; 1992.IA.03; 1998.IA.07)
    - J. Paul Getty shipboard as a young adult, undated; (3 photographic negatives) (Box 2010.IA.17-06, Section Set A)
    - Souvenir photographs of J. Paul Getty and guests at various nightclubs, 1950s; undated; (10 black-and-white photographic prints of various sizes enclosed in cardstock frames imprinted with nightclub logos) (Box 2010.IA.17-03)
    - J. Paul Getty with first wife, Jeanette Demont, undated; (1 photographic negative) (Box 2010.IA.17-06, Section Set H)
    - J. Paul Getty at his desk, circa 1939-1945 (Box Shared 1986.IA.22-02; 1987.IA.11; 1992.IA.03; 1998.IA.07)
    - J. Paul Getty at work, traveling, and at leisure, 1935; 1949,; undated; (approximately 30 black-and-white photographic prints, various sizes) (Box 2010.IA.17-06)
      Includes snapshots of Getty with former wife, Allene, and with unidentified women and children.
    - J. Paul Getty in swimsuit, undated; (1 photographic negative) (Box 2010.IA.17-06, Section Set B)
    - J. Paul Getty in front of automobile and in front of low stone wall, undated; (2 photographic negatives) (Box 2010.IA.17-06, Section Set B)
    - J. Paul Getty in front of automobile, undated; (3 photographic negatives) (Box 2010.IA.17-06, Section Set C)
    - J. Paul Getty at beach, undated; (2 photographic negatives) (Box 2010.IA.17-06, Section Set C)
    - J. Paul Getty in front of automobile and in front of stone wall, undated; (1 photographic negative) (Box 2010.IA.17-06, Section Set D)
    - J. Paul Getty in front of equine statues, undated; (1 photographic negative) (Box 2010.IA.17-06, Section Set D)
    - J. Paul Getty with dog (landscape in background), undated; (1 photographic negative) (Box 2010.IA.17-06, Section Set F)
    - J. Paul Getty with dog (on tennis court?), undated; (1 photographic negative) (Box 2010.IA.17-06, Section Set G)
    - J. Paul Getty at beach, undated; (1 photographic negative) (Box 2010.IA.17-06, Section Set G)
    - J. Paul Getty with landscape in background, undated; (1 photographic negative) (Box 2010.IA.17-06, Section Set H)
    - J. Paul Getty portrait in profile, 1939 (Box Shared 1986.IA.22-02; 1987.IA.11; 1992.IA.03; 1998.IA.07)
    - J. Paul Getty portraits taken at Sutton Place, undated; (3 photographic prints and corresponding negatives) (Box 2007.IA.32-01)
    - J. Paul Getty and guests at Sutton Place, including Getty Villa planning meetings, undated; (10 photographic prints and corresponding negatives) (Box 2007.IA.32-01)
    - J. Paul Getty hosting annual Christmas party for children at Sutton Place, undated; (4 photographic prints and corresponding negatives) (Box 2007.IA.32-01)
    - J. Paul Getty color portraits taken at Sutton Place, 1970s; (5 photographic prints and corresponding negatives) (Box 2007.IA.32-01)
    - J. Paul Getty with Richard M. Nixon, undated; (1 photographic print and corresponding negative) (Box Shared 1986.IA.48-12; 2002.IA.02, Folder 1)
    - J. Paul Getty with son and others, undated; (6 photographic prints and 2 negatives) (Box Shared 1986.IA.48-12; 2002.IA.02, Folder 1)
    - J. Paul Getty presenting trophy to Boyer Coe, Mr. Universe (London), 1973; (2 photographic prints and one document) (Box Shared 1986.IA.22-02; 1987.IA.11; 1992.IA.03; 1998.IA.07)
    - J. Paul Getty headshot (pinstriped suit), undated; (1 photographic print) (Box 1986.IA.48-11)
    - J. Paul Getty standing on a country road in front of barbed wire fence, undated; (1 photographic print with corresponding negative) (Box 1986.IA.48-11)
    - J. Paul Getty in his estate golf cart, the "Getty-up,", undated; (1 contact print and corresponding negative) (Box 1986.IA.48-11)
    - J. Paul Getty receiving an honorary degree, undated (Box Shared 1986.IA.48-12; 2002.IA.02)
      See original photograph in Hewins collection.
    - Coffin at Getty Villa burial site, undated; (2 color slides) (Box Shared 1987.IA.16-01; 2004.IA.17; 2009.IA.36; 2011.IA.44; 2022.IA.88)
      J. Paul Getty and his sons George F. Getty II and Timothy Ware Getty are buried at the site.
  - Travel and leisure:
    - Sarah C., George F., and J. Paul Getty tour of Europe, probably 1909
      Comprises images from the Getty family vacation in the summer of 1909. Includes images of George, Sarah, and Paul (from a distance) in a Chadwick touring car and scenes of Paris, Avignon, Holland, "Strassburg," Stratford on Avon, Oxford, the Rhine River, the Maas River, Monte Carlo, and "the Alps." Includes one picture of 17-year-old Paul in the driver's seat of the car with the Monte Carlo Casino in the background.
      - Prints, (approximately 14 photographic prints) (Box 2010.IA.17-06)
      - Negatives, (approximately 27 photographic negatives) (Box 2010.IA.17-06, Section Set A)
    - Snapshots of unidentified scenes, people, and animals (including a chimpanzee), undated; (approximately 8 photographic prints) (Box 2010.IA.17-06)
    - European athletic team (weightlifters and perhaps swimmers) group photos and beach scenes, undated; (approximately 16 photographic negatives) (Box 2010.IA.17-06, Section Set B)
    - Unidentified beach and outdoor scene, undated; (2 photographic negatives) (Box 2010.IA.17-06, Section Set C)
    - European cityscapes, undated; (2 photographic negatives) (Box 2010.IA.17-06, Section Set D)
    - European landscapes and street scenes, often featuring an unidentified woman, undated; (approximately 15 photographic negatives) (Box 2010.IA.17-06, Section Set E)
    - Ancient ruins and harbor scenes (possibly Herculaneum), undated; (approximately 12 photographic negatives) (Box 2010.IA.17-06, Section Set F)
    - Ancient ruins (amphitheatre, aquaduct, and other structures), harbor scenes, street scenes, and volcano, (possibly including Herculaneum), undated; (approximately 38 photographic negatives) (Box 2010.IA.17-06, Section Set G)
    - Ancient ruins, landscapes, cityscapes, and street scenes, undated; (14 photographic negatives) (Box 2010.IA.17-06, Section Set H)
      General
      Images are dark and difficult to identify.
    - Photographic postcards, 1934; undated; (11 photographic postcards, sepia and black-and-white) (Box 2010.IA.17-06)
      Sepia postcards depict scenes from Duvall, Wisconsin and unidentified persons. Black-and-white postcards depict Hearst Castle (California), a German train, and Swiss mountain scenes. Some of the postcards are annotated and one is signed "Edith," but none of them have been addressed or posted.
    - Various shots, including rowing, ruins, St Mark's (Venice), ships, a beach (Bahamas), and Hearst Castle, undated; (7 photographic prints and 1 photographic postcard) (Box 1986.IA.48-11)
    - New York City and Harbor, 1892; 1909,; undated; (4 photographic prints) (Box 1986.IA.48-11)
  - J. Paul Getty Museum:
    - Museum staff, including Stephen Garrett, Gillian Wilson, Jiri Frel, and others, 1970s; (5 photographic prints with corresponding negatives) (Box 2007.IA.32-01)
    - Ranch House galleries, undated; (5 photographic prints) (Box Shared 1986.IA.48-12; 2002.IA.02, Folder 3)
    - Ranch House: Louis XVI Gallery, undated; (7 photographic prints) (Box Shared 1986.IA.48-12; 2002.IA.02, Folder 2)
    - Exterior views of J. Paul Getty's Malibu Ranch House, undated; (4 photographic prints with corresponding negatives) (Box 1986.IA.48-11)
    - Museum staff: curator Jiri Frel, undated; (1 photographic print) (Box 1986.IA.48-11)
    - Ranch House zoo feeding (bear?), undated; (1 photographic print) (Box 1986.IA.48-11)
    - Ranch House painting gallery, undated; (1 photographic print) (Box 1986.IA.48-11)
    - Interior Ranch House: Guests touring J. Paul Getty Museum and Ethel Le Vane signing book (Collector's Choice), circa 1956; (6 photographic prints and corresponding negatives) (Box 1986.IA.48-11)
    - Ranch House zoo: bear and bison, undated; (2 color slides) (Box Shared 1987.IA.16-01; 2004.IA.17; 2009.IA.36; 2011.IA.44; 2022.IA.88)
  - Art objects:
    - French furniture images [sent from JPG to David S. Hecht?], undated; (6 photographic negatives) (Box Shared 1986.IA.22-02; 1987.IA.11; 1992.IA.03; 1998.IA.07)
    - Detail of tapestry at Sutton Place (color), undated; (1 photographic print and corresponding negative) (Box 2007.IA.32-01)
    - Queen Anne oak panelled room with fireplace (possible model for renovation of "Getty dining room"), undated; (1 photographic print and corresponding negative) (Box Shared 1986.IA.48-12; 2002.IA.02, Folder 4)
    - Unidentified tables (French decorative arts), undated; (6 photographic prints) (Box 1986.IA.48-11)
    - Unidentified statues on pedestals, undated; (1 photographic print) (Box 1986.IA.48-11)
  - Getty family:
    - George F. and Sarah C. Getty in automobile (San Diego, California), undated; (1 photographic print) (Box 2010.IA.17-06)
    - George F. Getty, I portrait, undated; (1 black-and-white photographic print) (Box 2010.IA.17-06)
    - Sarah C. Getty portrait in pearl necklace, circa 1880s; (1 photographic print and corresponding negative) (Box Shared 1986.IA.22-02; 1987.IA.11; 1992.IA.03; 1998.IA.07)
    - Sarah C. Getty (?) shipboard, undated; (2 photographic negatives) (Box 2010.IA.17-06, Section Set A)
    - Sarah C. Getty in armchair, interior of 647 South Kingsley Drive, undated; (1 photographic print) (Box 2010.IA.17-06)
    - Sarah C. Getty in armchair, interior of 647 South Kingsley Drive (enlargement), undated; (1 photographic print and corresponding negative) (Box Shared 1986.IA.22-02; 1987.IA.11; 1992.IA.03; 1998.IA.07)
    - George F. Getty II portrait, July 29, 1967; (1 color photographic print) (Box Shared 1986.IA.22-02; 1987.IA.11; 1992.IA.03; 1998.IA.07)
    - George F. Getty II portrait with Dalmation, undated (Box Shared 1986.IA.22-02; 1987.IA.11; 1992.IA.03; 1998.IA.07)
    - George F. Getty II with puppies (Midland, Texas), circa 1951-1952; (1 photographic print) (Box 2010.IA.17-06)
    - Crosshatch portraits of infant sons, undated; (Photographs of two unsigned drawings and one photographic negative) (Box Shared 1986.IA.22-02; 1987.IA.11; 1992.IA.03; 1998.IA.07)
    - Portrait of son with Scottish Terrier, undated; (1 photographic print) (Box Shared 1986.IA.22-02; 1987.IA.11; 1992.IA.03; 1998.IA.07)
    - Portrait of wife and infant son, undated; (1 photographic print) (Box Shared 1986.IA.22-02; 1987.IA.11; 1992.IA.03; 1998.IA.07)
    - Images of J. Paul Getty's grown sons and other family members at Sutton Place, undated; (5 photographic prints and corresponding negatives) (Box 2007.IA.32-01)
    - Teddy Getty dancing aboard the Queen Mary, undated; (1 photographic print, 5 x 7 inches) (Box 2010.IA.17-06)
    - Allene Ashby, undated; (2 hand-tinted photographic prints) (Box Shared 1986.IA.48-12; 2002.IA.02, Folder 5)
  - Getty residences:
    Images of Getty's Ranch House near Malibu, California have been placed with images of the J. Paul Getty Museum (above).